<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cloud on João Blasques | AI-Enabled Data Engineer</title><link>https://joaoblasques.com/tags/cloud/</link><description>Recent content in Cloud on João Blasques | AI-Enabled Data Engineer</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://joaoblasques.com/tags/cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building a Data Pipeline with BigQuery: From Storage to Analytics</title><link>https://joaoblasques.com/post/data-warehouse-bigquery-pipeline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://joaoblasques.com/post/data-warehouse-bigquery-pipeline/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="project-overview">Project Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This project demonstrates the implementation of a comprehensive data pipeline using Google BigQuery as the primary data warehouse solution. The pipeline showcases modern data engineering practices including external data integration, table optimization strategies, and performance tuning techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Repository:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/jonasblasques/4-data-pipeline-datawarehouse-bigquery">Data Pipeline with BigQuery&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project focuses on building a scalable, cost-effective data warehouse solution that can handle large volumes of NYC taxi trip data while maintaining optimal query performance and cost efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-concepts">Key Concepts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>• &lt;strong>OLAP vs OLTP:&lt;/strong> Understanding the fundamental differences between Online Analytical Processing and Online Transaction Processing systems
• &lt;strong>Data Warehousing:&lt;/strong> Implementing centralized storage for analytical workloads with optimized query performance
• &lt;strong>Table Partitioning:&lt;/strong> Dividing large tables into manageable chunks based on time or range values
• &lt;strong>Clustering:&lt;/strong> Organizing data within partitions to improve query performance and reduce costs
• &lt;strong>External Tables:&lt;/strong> Querying data stored outside BigQuery without incurring storage costs
• &lt;strong>Performance Optimization:&lt;/strong> Implementing best practices for cost reduction and query efficiency&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>